<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Michael Evans]]></title>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-08T11:33:08-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://michaelevans.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Evans]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2013 in Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/12/31/2013-in-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T11:27:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2013/12/31/2013-in-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is December 31st, and I decided to write up a blog post, reflecting on the year that I&rsquo;ve had. I&rsquo;ve learned a lot over the last twelve months, and done a lot of interesting things (okay, at least interesting to me). Here&rsquo;s a brief overview of what happened:</p>

<p><div align='center'><div class='g-post' data-href='https://plus.google.com/114052868601022948953/posts/ZzXcKVs2fvH'></div></div></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Looking Back</h2>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>January 17th</strong>: Released the first version of my <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.evans.hackernews">Hacker News</a> app to the Play Store. It was one of my first Android releases in a long while, and my first using the &ldquo;Holo&rdquo; design language that came about in Android 4.0+. It was met with a surprising amount of positivity when I <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5072757">posted it on Hacker News</a>, and has a 4.1 rating as of this post. I am actually in the process of rewriting this app, using a lot of the techniques I learned in the past 12 months.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>February</strong>: In February I was invited to take part in the <a href="http://www.michaelevans.org/blog/2013/02/20/googles-project-glass/">Glass Foundry</a>, a hackathon for Google Glass. I was one of the first non-Googlers to get my hands on it, and the team I was on won! Our prize was a Google Glass, free of charge. We built a recipes app for Glass, which would allow for hands-free cooking.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>April</strong>: April was a pretty exciting month for me, I quit my job as a developer at The Washington Post, and started a new one as a developer at LivingSocial. I also traveled to New York City, in order to be one of the first people to pick up <a href="http://www.michaelevans.org/blog/2013/04/29/hands-on-with-google-glass/">Google Glass</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>May</strong>: In May, I was fortunate enough to attend my third Google I/O. If you know anything about Google I/O, you&rsquo;d know that statement alone is enough.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>August</strong>: After returning from Defcon 21, I posted <a href="http://www.michaelevans.org/blog/2013/08/14/tutorial-building-an-android-to-do-list-app-using-parse/">a pair</a> of <a href="http://www.michaelevans.org/blog/2013/08/20/parse-android-todo-app-tutorial-part-two-users/">Android development tutorials</a> on how to make a Todo application using Parse. These have been two of my most popular posts to date, and I&rsquo;ll definitely be working on more in the future. If you enjoyed those posts, feel free to let me know what other topics you&rsquo;d like to see covered!</p></li>
<li><p><strong>September</strong>: After a bit of a hiatus from Android app development, I released an app called <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.michaelevans.bikefinder">Bike Finder</a>. This app is for locating bikes for use with Capital Bikeshare in Washington DC, with support for CityBikes and Divvy (among others) soon.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>October</strong>: Another hackathon attempt, this time without success; Ed, Jon and I built an app for BattleHack called Tappd, which was designed to be a point-of-sale replacement, where users could tap-to-pay, as well as recieve push notifications for events such as their table being ready.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>November</strong>: I signed up and was chosen to be one of the <a href="https://helpouts.google.com/114052868601022948953/ls/a65184ab017ae8b0">pioneer providers</a> for Google Helpouts, a program designed to help people in real time, using Google Hangouts. I set up a helpout to teach software development, and have had a few dozen <a href="http://blog.votanoticias.com/app-de-meneame-para-google-glass/">successful sessions</a> so far.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>December</strong>: Most recently I released my first open source library for Android: <a href="https://github.com/MichaelEvans/ColorArt">ColorArt</a>. It ended up being very popular, making it onto <a href="http://androidweekly.net/issues/issue-81">Android Weekly</a>, and being the top Java repo for a week on GitHub. And even more exciting was the release of a project I had been working on for 3 months: a complete rewrite of the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.livingsocial.www">LivingSocial app for Android</a>. It was a big update for us, and even got featured on one of my favorite Android news sites: <a href="http://www.androidpolice.com/2013/12/10/livingsocial-hits-v2-0-gets-a-complete-redesign-and-deal-searching/">Android Police</a>.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Going Forward</h3>

<p>For 2014, I&rsquo;d really like to contribute more to open source. Much of the work I do takes advantage of the work that others have open sourced, and I really find contributing back rewarding. I&rsquo;d also like to do more writing on this blog, with both personal posts, as well as more tips and tutorials.</p>

<p>Overall, 2013 was a pretty eventful year. Here&rsquo;s to 2014 being even better. Happy New Year everyone!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
