<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Kotlin | Michael Evans]]></title>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/categories/kotlin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://michaelevans.org/"/>
  <updated>2025-07-13T00:35:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://michaelevans.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Evans]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smooth Theme Transitions in Compose with Animated ColorSchemes]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2025/07/11/smooth-theme-transitions-in-compose-with-animated-colorschemes/"/>
    <updated>2025-07-11T23:38:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2025/07/11/smooth-theme-transitions-in-compose-with-animated-colorschemes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If your Jetpack Compose app supports light and dark themes, you’ve probably noticed the default behavior: a sudden cut between color schemes when the system UI mode changes.</p>

<p>I think we&rsquo;ve all seen theme changes that look like this:</p>

<p><video width='270' height='600' preload='none' controls ><source src='/images/2025/07/01/instant.webm' type='video/webm; codecs=vp8, vorbis'>Your browser does not support the video tag.</video></p>

<p>We can do better.</p>

<p>By wrapping your theme setup with some animation, we can achieve <strong>smooth transitions between light and dark themes</strong> that feel much more polished — without rebuilding your entire app structure.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<h2>The Idea: Animate the ColorScheme</h2>

<p>Jetpack Compose’s <code>MaterialTheme</code> accepts a <code>ColorScheme</code>. If we gradually animate the colors inside that scheme when the system toggles between dark and light, we can fade the colors smoothly across the entire app.</p>

<p>Here’s a simplified example:</p>

<p>```
@Composable
fun AnimatedTheme(</p>

<pre><code>darkTheme: Boolean = isSystemInDarkTheme(),
content: @Composable () -&gt; Unit
</code></pre>

<p>) {</p>

<pre><code>val targetScheme = if (darkTheme) DarkColorScheme else LightColorScheme

val animatedScheme = targetScheme.copy(
    primary = animateColorAsState(targetScheme.primary).value,
    background = animateColorAsState(targetScheme.background).value,
    surface = animateColorAsState(targetScheme.surface).value,
    onPrimary = animateColorAsState(targetScheme.onPrimary).value,
    // Add more swatches as needed...
)

MaterialTheme(
    colorScheme = animatedScheme,
    typography = Typography,
    shapes = Shapes,
    content = content
)
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>You can expand this to include all 20+ color swatches if you want — but we’ll show a better way shortly.</p>

<hr />

<h2>The Problem: Too Many Animations</h2>

<p>Manually animating every color swatch with <code>animateColorAsState</code> works, but:</p>

<ul>
<li>It’s <strong>verbose</strong></li>
<li>It runs <strong>a lot of recompositions</strong> (even for unused swatches)</li>
<li>It can be <strong>hard to keep up</strong> if <code>ColorScheme</code> changes</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h2>A Better Approach: Animating with updateTransition</h2>

<p>A cleaner solution is to animate all properties as part of a single <code>Transition</code>. That way, Compose shares the animation clock and easing, and you&rsquo;re not scattering a dozen independent animation calls.</p>

<p>```
private fun defaultColorTransitionSpec(): FiniteAnimationSpec<Color> =</p>

<pre><code>tween(durationMillis = 500, easing = LinearOutSlowInEasing)
</code></pre>

<p>@Composable
fun AnimatedTheme(</p>

<pre><code>darkTheme: Boolean = isSystemInDarkTheme(),
content: @Composable () -&gt; Unit
</code></pre>

<p>) {</p>

<pre><code>val targetScheme = if (darkTheme) DarkColorScheme else LightColorScheme
val transition = updateTransition(targetScheme, label = "themeTransition")

val primary by transition.animateColor(
    label = "primary",
    transitionSpec = { defaultColorTransitionSpec() }) { it.primary }
val background by transition.animateColor(
    label = "background",
    transitionSpec = { defaultColorTransitionSpec() }) { it.background }
val surface by transition.animateColor(
    label = "surface",
    transitionSpec = { defaultColorTransitionSpec() }) { it.surface }
val onPrimary by transition.animateColor(
    label = "onPrimary",
    transitionSpec = { defaultColorTransitionSpec() }) { it.onPrimary }

val animatedScheme = targetScheme.copy(
    primary = primary,
    background = background,
    surface = surface,
    onPrimary = onPrimary
)
MaterialTheme(colorScheme = animatedScheme, content = content)
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This version:</p>

<ul>
<li>Uses a single <code>Transition</code> to group related animations</li>
<li>Shares the same easing/duration across all swatches</li>
<li>Is easier to extend or modify incrementally</li>
</ul>


<p>After we add our animations, it will look more like this:</p>

<p><video width='270' height='600' preload='none' controls ><source src='/images/2025/07/01/animated.webm' type='video/webm; codecs=vp8, vorbis'>Your browser does not support the video tag.</video></p>

<hr />

<h2>Final Notes</h2>

<ul>
<li>If you want to animate <strong>all</strong> color properties, you&rsquo;ll still need to call <code>animateColor</code> for each one — but this pattern scales better than copy-pasting 25 <code>animateColorAsState</code> calls.</li>
<li>For most apps, animating just a <strong>handful</strong> of swatches (<code>primary</code>, <code>background</code>, <code>surface</code>, <code>onPrimary</code>, <code>error</code>) gives most of the perceived polish.</li>
<li>Avoid using reflection or deep copying here — it’s better to be explicit and in control of what’s animated.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h2>Wrap-Up</h2>

<p>This technique brings a much smoother feel to your app, especially if your users frequently switch between light and dark mode (or you support a manual toggle).</p>

<p>(Hopefully the Compose team eventually provides a helper for this boilerplate.)</p>

<p>Happy theming!</p>

<h2>Sample Code</h2>

<p>Want to try it out yourself? I’ve published a small sample project on GitHub that demonstrates both animated and non-animated theme switching:</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/MichaelEvans/AnimatedThemeExample">View the sample project on GitHub</a></p>

<p>It includes the exact code from this post and the toggle UI shown in the GIFs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Turning Any Android Callback into a Flow with callbackFlow]]></title>
    <link href="http://michaelevans.org/blog/2025/03/22/turning-any-android-callback-into-a-flow-with-callbackflow/"/>
    <updated>2025-03-22T23:10:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://michaelevans.org/blog/2025/03/22/turning-any-android-callback-into-a-flow-with-callbackflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve been working with Android for any amount of time, you&rsquo;ve probably run into APIs that expose their results using callbacks or listeners. Whether it&rsquo;s something like <code>LocationManager</code>, a custom SDK, or a third-party service like Firebase, you&rsquo;re often stuck adapting old-school async patterns into your modern reactive code.</p>

<p>This approach is especially helpful in apps using Jetpack Compose, coroutines, or unidirectional data flow.</p>

<p>Fortunately, Kotlin&rsquo;s <code>callbackFlow</code> makes this much easier. In this post, we&rsquo;ll show how to wrap a listener-based API using <code>callbackFlow</code>, so you can collect updates as a <code>Flow</code>. We&rsquo;ll use the Firebase Realtime Database as an example, but this pattern works for nearly anything.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Problem: Listeners Aren’t Reactive</h2>

<p>Here’s the classic way of listening to changes in the Firebase Realtime Database:</p>

<p>```
val postListener = object : ValueEventListener {</p>

<pre><code>override fun onDataChange(dataSnapshot: DataSnapshot) {
    val post = dataSnapshot.getValue&lt;Post&gt;()
    // update UI
}

override fun onCancelled(error: DatabaseError) {
    Log.w(TAG, "loadPost:onCancelled", error.toException())
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
postReference.addValueEventListener(postListener)
```</p>

<p>This works fine — but it’s imperative and not easily composable with things like <code>StateFlow</code>, <code>LiveData</code>, or Jetpack Compose. Let’s fix that.</p>

<h2>The Fix: Wrap It with callbackFlow</h2>

<p>Kotlin’s <code>callbackFlow</code> is designed for exactly this kind of situation — where you need to bridge a listener-based API into a reactive stream.</p>

<p>Here’s what it looks like for Firebase:</p>

<p>```
fun Query.asFlow(): Flow<DataSnapshot> = callbackFlow {</p>

<pre><code>val listener = object : ValueEventListener {
    override fun onDataChange(snapshot: DataSnapshot) {
        trySend(snapshot).isSuccess // emit each snapshot into the Flow
    }

    override fun onCancelled(error: DatabaseError) {
        close(error.toException()) // cancel the flow on error
    }
}

// Start listening for updates
addValueEventListener(listener)

// Suspend until the flow is closed or cancelled, then clean up
awaitClose { removeEventListener(listener) }
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Let’s break that down:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>callbackFlow { ... }</code>: Gives you a coroutine-safe way to emit values (<code>send</code> / <code>trySend</code>) from a callback-based API.</li>
<li><code>trySend(snapshot)</code>: Emits a value into the flow. This is non-blocking and returns a <code>ChannelResult</code>, which we&rsquo;re ignoring here.</li>
<li><code>close(error.toException())</code>: If the Firebase listener is cancelled, we close the flow with the exception. This cancels any active collectors.</li>
<li><code>awaitClose { ... }</code>: Suspends the coroutine until the collector stops collecting (i.e., it’s cancelled or the flow completes), and is the right place to clean up listeners or resources.</li>
</ul>


<p>The result is a clean <code>Flow&lt;DataSnapshot&gt;</code> that behaves just like you’d want: it emits every time Firebase sends an update and automatically stops listening when the consumer stops collecting.</p>

<h2>Consuming the Flow</h2>

<p>You can now collect this from anywhere in your app. Here’s a quick example:</p>

<p>```
lifecycleScope.launch {</p>

<pre><code>postReference.asFlow().collect { snapshot -&gt;
    val post = snapshot.getValue&lt;Post&gt;()
    // Update UI or state
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This could also be collected in a <code>ViewModel</code>, transformed with <code>map</code>, or turned into Compose <code>State</code>. But that’s outside the scope of this post — we just wanted to show the full round trip here.</p>

<h2>A Note on <code>.snapshots</code></h2>

<p>If you’re using the Firebase Realtime Database, you might have seen the (relatively new) <code>snapshots</code> extension, which does exactly this out of the box:</p>

<p><code>
postReference.snapshots.collect { snapshot -&gt; /* ... */ }
</code></p>

<p>So if you’re only dealing with Firebase, you might not need your own wrapper. But the <code>callbackFlow</code> approach is still incredibly useful for any API that doesn’t have a ready-made Flow extension.</p>

<h2>Wrap-Up</h2>

<p><code>callbackFlow</code> is a powerful tool for adapting listener-based or callback-heavy APIs into clean, composable Kotlin Flows. Once you wrap something like this, you can:</p>

<ul>
<li>Collect updates in your <code>ViewModel</code> or UI layer</li>
<li>Combine it with other Flows</li>
<li>Debounce, map, retry, or buffer updates</li>
</ul>


<p>Firebase was just the example here — but this trick works great for things like:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>SensorManager</code></li>
<li><code>TextWatcher</code></li>
<li><code>LocationManager</code></li>
<li>WebSocket libraries</li>
<li>Custom event systems</li>
</ul>


<p>Once you get used to wrapping listeners this way, it’s hard to go back.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
